Hello world. If you've ever visited
Japan before, one of the things on your
bucket list was probably to ride on the
ultraast Shinkansen. And it would be
pretty hard to avoid riding on the metro
or subway lines. If, like most tourists,
you started your Japan trip in Tokyo.
But have you ever ridden on the tinier,
slower trains that run through rice
patties, mountain sides, and sleepy
towns? These rural train lines called
Chihosen are probably what you imagine
when you think of a Studio Ghibli movie.
These trains, despite being relatively
old, continue to run all across the
country, transporting tens of thousands
of people to crucial transfer locations
every day. Though not as flashy or
frequent as their modern counterparts,
these local trains play an important
part of keeping rural economies and
communities alive. But in the last few
decades, many of these rural train lines
have started to shut down with over
1,200 km of rail disappearing since the
year 2000. That's [music] like the
distance from Tokyo to Fukuoka. But that
said, there's still a lot of train rails
left in Japan, over 25,000 km worth,
which is like 2/3 of the Earth's
circumference. So, for this video, I
wanted to investigate why there's so
much rail in Japan and how these various
train lines continue to operate. But
first, let me introduce this video
sponsor. It's us. My family just built
and opened [music]
this mini hotel called Silver Daisy Stay
Niko. Getting to Niko from Tokyo is easy
as there are some cool express trains
like the futuristic and swanky Spacia X,
the well also futuristic looking Revity,
or the classic Keon. And once you're
here, if you're looking for something
really classic, there's the Taiu DL and
SL. DL standing for diesel locomotive
and SL for steam locomotive.
Okay, let's get going by defining what
we'll call a local train line, a
chihosen. Here's the three criteria we
chose. One, the train line doesn't run
through heavily populated areas. Two, as
a general rule, local trains are
unprofitable, even when they run at
maximum efficiency. And three, if you
see a train that has three cars or
fewer, it's probably a local train. Now,
how and why in the world did all of
Japan's train infrastructure get built
to begin with? Well, Reese from RM
Transit is going to help us answer this.
So, a big part of it is that rails were
built as speculative investments a lot
of the time. And you know, like people
built them and they went bankrupt in a
lot of cases, but we still have the
rails and and the the expensive stuff
got built. And so once you have that,
continuing to operate it and maintain it
isn't super expensive. You know, of
course, relative to building something
brand new. And then of course there's
there's the population decline factor,
right? Like a lot of these rail lines
probably made more sense when there were
more people living in various areas, but
also when you think about it as a
speculative investment that's often
related to real estate, there's often a
belief that hey, if we build a rail line
here, like that's going to lead to a new
town developing or it's going to lead to
a new housing development and that's
going to fund things, right? And so in
many cases, you know, these rail lines
just might have not, you know, paid off.
In some cases, they had different uh
different uses originally, right? Some
of them were kind of like street car
lines that got upgraded over time. And
so, basically, what I would say is that
no one really planned or predicted the
way that things would end up today. And
that's part of why it doesn't
necessarily feel like it makes a ton of
sense or that it's like kind of
economically viable. And it's just
because Japan ended up with a lot of
rail and now it's got a surplus. And
it's sort of like how do we keep this
running? uh especially because it's not
like the alternatives have stayed still.
>> And to dig even deeper, let's go back to
the very beginning and talk about how
trains got their start in Japan since
they definitely weren't invented here.
To answer this, we have to go back to
the Maji period in the 1870s. On October
14th, 1872, the first ever Japanese
train line, the Tokaido line, was
opened, connecting Shimbashi to
Yokohama. It spanned 29 km and was built
with the help of British engineers. In
fact, the locomotives themselves were
even imported from the UK because there
were no train [music] manufacturing
facilities in Japan yet. As no rail
companies existed in Japan, this was all
backed by the Japanese Imperial
government. And they made sure that the
British engineers taught their Japanese
colleagues everything they knew so that
Japan's railways could be
self-sufficient.
And so by 1889, the Tokaido line had
connected Tokyo to Nagagoya, Kyoto,
Coobe, and Osaka, and private railway
companies had started to operate
throughout Japan. By 1906, the Japanese
government railways RJGR unified all
private railways to help supply military
bases and ports to feed Japan's
military-industrial complex. But after
World War II, with the nation's economy
in shambles, JGR was reorganized into a
state-owned public corporation called
Japanese National Railways or JNR. It's
a bit complicated, but basically JNR was
able to operate like a business by
expanding and modernizing its rail
services across the country, but at the
same time, it tried to fulfill its
public duty to provide affordable rail
access [music] to rural communities,
which were generally unprofitable. And
in 1964, the famous Shinkansen was
launched for the Tokyo Olympics thanks
to JNR research and development. Fun
fact, the grandmother and mother of our
part-time producer Bobby rode the
Shinkansen from Nagoya to watch the
Tokyo Olympics that year. Anyway,
despite all of its rail expansion
throughout the 1970s and 80s, JNR faced
massive financial problems. We're
talking a jaw-dropping $250 billion of
debt. Much of this debt was due to
decades of mismanagement of funds that
ballooned over time due to compounding
interest rates. Other factors like
increased car ownership and convenient
freight trucks had chipped away at train
ridership and freight profits. [music]
So to address this giant fiscal problem,
the government split JNR into nine
entities with six main passenger
companies including JR East, Central
West, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Hokkaido. The
other three entities were JR freight, JR
Technical Research Institute, and the
JNR Settlement Corporation. The
government was hoping that the more
profitable JR companies like JR East,
Central, and West with their Shinkansen
lines would eventually become publicly
traded companies on the Japanese stock
exchange. After their initial public
offerings, the government sold off their
shares of their JR companies to public
investors for a decent sum of money. But
even then, they could only pay off about
onethird of the debt. The remaining 150
to200 billion dollars was to be paid by
taxpayers starting in 1998 and
continuing to this day. This, as you
could imagine, was a controversial
decision. From the government's
perspective, by wiping out the debt that
JR had created, the modern JR companies,
especially JR East, Central, and West,
could now be profitable and thrive on
their own. But from the public's
perspective, they had just bailed out a
ton of government-made mismanaged debt
so that private companies could profit
from their tax money. And in case you
were curious, JRushu eventually became
profitable enough to go public and
become a [music] private company in
2016. Meanwhile, JR Shikoku and Hokkaido
have remained under government ownership
because they're simply not profitable.
So, how does all of this relate to local
train lines to Chihosen? Well, roughly
70% of Japan's railway network is owned
and managed by JR groups. And many of
these train lines are local lines with
fewer and fewer passengers every year,
putting them in danger of closure. And
to help explain this, we talked to
Steve, a transportation engineer.
>> So, essentially JR Group, one of the
norms they created was that if the
ridership density of a line is less than
4,000 per day, you can consider it for
closure.
>> A daily wrership density of 4,000 simply
means that 4,000 passengers travel
across the entirety of the track every
day. So if on average a passenger only
travels half the length of the tracks,
you would need 8,000 passengers to hit a
passenger density of 4,000. But this was
created in the 80s or '7s. But a lot of
operators took that as a hard line. So
Betsu was big on this and then they said
this is less than 4,000. We're going to
close it. But that was just a rule of
thumb. It's not legally binding. And
then the other thing they look at is
operating ratio, which is the cost
divided by revenue multiplied by 100. If
you have an operating ratio of 100, it
would simply mean that expenses equals
revenue. So not losing money but not
making money. Less than 100 is good.
You're making money. Over 100 is bad.
You're losing money. like they'll take
into account if it gets to like you know
a thousand which is you're you're losing
like for every hundred yen you're losing
like a,000 yen which a lot of lines are
you know that they maybe consider other
things like for example the passenger
density is the big one. So if you have a
limited express which is long distance
carrying 600 people from one end of the
line to the other that really pumps up
your numbers right as opposed to lots of
little short runs of a line. So to give
a real life example of what Steve means
with passenger density let's look at the
Chisu Express. There are 14 local stops
along the Chisu Express route spanning
56 km. These trains mainly service
students, seniors, and locals commuting
to work. They may be relatively full in
the morning and evening, but during the
afternoon they are pretty empty. This
makes the passenger density of the local
line quite low. However, the Express in
Chisu Express comes from having two
rapid trains run through their train
tracks, the Super Inaba and the Super
Hakut. These two rapid trains not only
get high ridership, but they quickly
cover the entirety of the tracks, which
means the passenger density of the Chisu
Express can be hugely boosted with only
a few of the supers passing through. But
even with relatively high ridership, it
doesn't guarantee that a train line is
safe from closure. the Railway Business
Act, which is the most kind of like the
the Bible of railway legal minutia in
Japan, they revised it to have a more
looser criteria for closer closure of
lines in the 2000s. So, article 28-2.
Now, to close a line, you just need to
notify the Ministry of Land,
Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism
one year in advance. And of course they
also have this caveat in the law that
you have to provide hearings and set up
committees to gather opinions from uh
relevant stakeholders usually local
governments. So the options are third
sectorization so public private
partnerships. The local government might
be interested in putting in some money
and it becomes like a spunoff company.
It has a nice name, some cool branding,
some logos and it becomes third
sectorized.
So, the Chisu Express is an example of a
third sector line, a partnership between
local government and a private company.
And in case you're wondering, first
sector would be government operated like
Tollway in Tokyo. And second sector
would be completely private like Tobu
Railway. As Steve mentioned, if a
private company chooses to no longer
operate a line, but local governments
need those services, the locals may
agree to help subsidize the line. And
quite often they run parallel to
Shinkansen lines like up in northern
Japan. The issue with this is that they
struggle to compete against the speedy
Shinkansen. But for locals who live in
between the major Shinkansen stops, it's
an important service. The other option
is more of the political option where
they kind of drag it on. They don't set
up the committee, right? And the the
railway kind of is stuck with this
railway. And this is kind of the more
passive aggressive method. And then the
last option is straight up closure. But
once a train line closes, it effectively
eliminates safe, affordable public
transit for communities near the train
line. But if various train lines
continue to close throughout Japan, what
will local people do to get around?
>> The aging population means a lot of
people are starting to not be able to
drive. You don't want a situation where
you have uh like elderly and rural areas
sort of trapped in their town. Before
railways, it would be they would visit
neighboring towns and stuff for events
and social kind of aspects. If you don't
have the railway anchoring the town and
everything, everything's just gone. You
you see a lot of national, you know,
along national routes, it's starting to
look like America. So, it's very going
to be very strip mall based. Japan has a
lot of roadways and it's built more and
more expressways every year. Even now,
like new expressways are built in places
where they compete with railways, right?
And so it's not like a it's not even
just the population declining in a lot
of smaller uh cities and towns, but it's
also that there are now there's another
option. And in a lot of these places,
you might take the train to go to the
next town, but like daytoday you're
probably driving, right? And so if you
already have the car, why wouldn't you
drive on the expressway instead of
paying for a ticket to take a once an
hour train, right? I personally saw this
when I was filming my documentary about
what a small town in Japan is like. The
town of Kofu has that train that runs
like once every hour and it services the
students and those without cars. But the
majority of people, especially those
working, would take their car into the
nearby city of Yono for work, shopping,
services, and fun. Whether we're
traveling for fun or for work, it's hard
to imagine Japan without its convenient
and charming network of trains. Another
thing to consider about the economic
benefit of keeping these local lines
alive is that the profitable Shinkansen
running through Osaka and Tokyo depend
on passengers that are transferring from
local train stations. Think of local
train lines as little blood vessels that
connect millions of people to the main
Shinkansen arteries of Japan. Sure, cars
or buses could in theory replace these
local lines, but just imagine how much
more congested roads and the areas near
the Shinkansen stations would get.
Anyway, it's not all doom and gloom.
There are smaller train lines like Chisu
Express that remain profitable year
after year if you ignore the first three
years of co [snorts]
Business
game.
Now, I think it's important to remind
you that Chisu Express and other public
private railways are financially
supported by local governments and Shizu
Express is fortunate to not have
competition from Shinkansen lines. For
example, up in the To<unk>hoku region,
Awe Mori railways has to compete against
the To<unk>hoku Shinkansen, which
inevitably wins over many potential
riders due to its speed, frequency, and
comfort. And a final thing to note is
that Chisu Express earns money from
lending out its tracks to JR West. If
for whatever reason GR West goes
bankrupt or stops running as many trains
through Chisu Express's tracks, it would
spell financial disaster. And speaking
of disasters, Steve had this to say
about railway maintenance.
>> The big threat is actually natural
disasters that what really actually
accelerates uh line closures, which
happened to a few uh third sector
railways. If a bridge collapses due to a
flood or earthquake, that line's not
viable anymore. So with all this
information in mind, whether it's
declining train ridership due to
increased motorways and shrinking
population, the increase in railway
closures since the 2000s or the
everlooming threat of natural disasters,
it may seem like there are too many
problems to fix. One potential solution
is the expansion of services near train
stations. It's the policy of putting
more development on stations that only
metropolitan areas really kind of got
down, right? The integrating bus and
railway together with a common fair like
you see that's that's not common in
Japan. Some of these areas they just
don't have the funds to say, you know,
there's a nice temple or a beach extend
that railway just like that that short 2
km. Like a lot of times it's like these
2 km gaps that you just like it's too
far to walk but it's also like too like
it feels bad to use a taxi and all that
stuff. Big tourist cities like Kyoto
Himeji do a pretty solid job of making
their bus systems intuitive and easy to
use for visitors and locals. But the
further out you go into rural areas, I
find that bus schedules can be difficult
to read, payment systems inconsistent,
and overall frequency to be less than
desirable. So even if they're operated
by different companies, perhaps a
well-integrated public transit system
will help all parties, including the
local economy. But if integrating other
modes of public transportation is one
viable option to increase train
ridership, what about those theme-based
train cars? One thing I was wondering
was there are lines, local lines I see
when I ride them, they're really trying
to attract tourists or hobbyists, and
they're trying to do like special events
surrounding the the train line, right?
So maybe they put like a a stove in it
and they're making fish on it or obey.
Are these actually successful or are
they just kind of like trying to do
stuff and they're not really working?
>> I was going to say I think this is kind
of like a very promising option, right?
Because Japan gets a ton of tourists.
Obviously now more than ever like people
are aware of this and that's a huge
potential market because people can ride
a train anywhere but Japan's got all
these super wacky and unique trains,
right? like it's constantly advertised
internationally. So I I think it's
actually a very good option. The key is
how do you parlay like running something
that's good for tourists and use it to
maybe maybe keep that thing still useful
for locals. So there has there has to be
some policy some some thinking about how
do we capture this tourist market and
use it to to fund important local
services.
But as important as profits are,
remember that trains in Japan weren't
always about making money. Initially,
they were an investment by the
government to advance Japan's technology
and infrastructure. So perhaps we're
living in another transition period of
Japan's train line history where it's
evolving from a profit-driven system
into something more along the lines of a
necessary public service.
>> But you have to understand that there's
a lot of benefits that a rail system
brings that are hard to quantify. the
subway doesn't um doesn't get to say
like uh we made x money on every ticket,
but also this person doesn't own a car
and that saved them all this money. It
saved society all this money. The
profitability is is useful in the sense
it's like measuring efficiency, but it
doesn't really measure whether it's
doing a good thing for a city or not,
right? Because there's so many things
that they just don't get to price in.
like what is the the cost benefit of
having less emissions, you know, having
a greener solution or what is the cost
benefit of, you know, being easily
usable by elderly people. Uh it makes it
so that young people can travel before
they can have a car, right? So, there's
all of these benefits that rail brings
that that are hard to quantify. Well, I
for one hope that Japan's local train
lines continue to exist and that they
find sustainable ways to keep them
operating into the future. And if you're
visiting Japan, I highly recommend
trying out some of these local train
lines. They're a great way to see
Japan's beautiful landscapes. Thanks for
watching. See you next time. Peace. What
are the local train lines like where
you're from?